over the last year I reviewed the
scientific literature of 11 supplements
and their effect on a number of outcomes
from heart disease to sleep to cognitive
effects and more in this video I'm going
to give you a brief breakdown from my
findings across all these supplements
and grade them based on two criteria one
what is the strength of evidence across
the studies that I analyzed and two what
is the effect size how much of an effect
this supplement actually provides that
said know that the conclusions are
limited to the outcomes assessed so if
you take torine for sciatic capan and
I'm discussing metabolic syndrome know
that the conclusion is only applying to
metabolic syndrome finally if you want
more specifics on any of these
supplements including having the data
broken down for you and access to the
studies I'll link my individual videos
for all of these supplements in the
pinned comment okay let's dive in
Omega-3s for heart health I analyzed
nine studies many of which were
metaanalyses including up to 30 studies
on the effect that Omega-3s have on
various forms of heart disease like
heart attack stroke and so on throughout
all these studies there seems to be good
evidence that Omega-3s in the form of
fish oil or otherwise reduces heart
disease risk in people with heart
disease the effect is small to moderate
but present across many analyses
including more rigorous analyses like
the Cochran Library unfortunately
there's also some evidence pointing to
Omega-3s can increase the risk of
irregular heart rhythms known as
fibrillation that point is still debated
however interestingly even with this
possible issue there is still an overall
protective effect of Omega-3s on
cardiovascular disease so everything
considered I scored Omega-3s as a B for
heart health glycine for sleep I
analyzed all the human studies that I
could find to date on glycine
supplementation on sleep across four
studies all of them indicated a
effectiveness of glycine for Sleep
however it might be important for you to
know that most of the studies were
industry Affiliated in addition while
there's clearly consistency across
studies the effect sizes in these
studies were honestly relatively small
so I scored glycine as a c for Sleep
based on the current
evidence toring for metabolic syndrome
for toring I went over one meta analysis
focused on a metabolic syndrome which is
essentially a a grouping of disorders
from diabetes to obesity to
cardiovascular disease in that analysis
including 25 randomized control trials
the researchers identifi torine
supplementation as providing multiple
benefits from reductions in blood
pressure uh reduced blood triglycerides
and a likely effect of reducing blood
sugar the effects were again mild but
since the effect was AC multiple
measures that's not so bad so that's a
point in favor of touring however
there's also a lot of heterogen or
inconsistency across studies so I think
that there's probably some more work
that needs to be done to find out why
studies are so all over the place for
example toring May provide more benefit
to people with heart disease than those
who are obese only we don't know that
yet even so it does seem that toring is
a benefit so I scored a B for metabolic
syndrome only detracting because of the
need for more data to tease out who
might benefit more than others aanan for
skin now if you're thinking why did you
look at aaz anthon for skin instead of
something like longevity or some other
outcome I hear you but this is what I
was interested in so here we are
although I did cover aaz anthon on
longevity for the physionic inside ERS
if you know you know it's linked in the
description anyway there's one analysis
of 11 studies and overall across three
measurements of skin health and age ases
anthon seem to provide a benefit in two
out of three measures unfortunately the
analysis was weakened because again
there's a lot of inconsistency across
studies and not all the studies were
well of the highest qu quality I also
don't think that the effect is very big
so all considered it seems that asto
santhon might help our skin but it
wouldn't be my go-to and the research
needs some work so I demoted aazan to a
d for skin based on the current research
that may change over time as we get more
studies Lion's man for cognitive
function this one is tricky lines man a
mushroom has been touted as having
several benefits but I focused on my
attention on the cognitive effects
across eight studies in different groups
of people lines man had disappointing
results for people who are young and
healthy there's one study that indicates
a pure benefit but if you look at the
effect size as measured it's
minuscule other studies indicate
improvements in some cognitive measures
and worsening of others or they just
show no effect at all however there is a
bit better evidence when looking at
people who are suffering from some form
of cognitive impairment like Dementia or
sleeping problems among others so I'm
inclined to split the score here for
healthy individuals with good sleep no
other cognitive obstructions the
evidence is very weak so I'd give it a d
on the other hand for people who have
some sort of cognitive dysfunction from
as little as sleep problems to more
serious situations like a full-blown
dementia I'd promote the evidence to AC
for those that might comment that they
swear by lions M keep in mind here that
there aren't many human studies so I'm
hamstrung by the limitations of the data
beta alling for performance for this one
I analyzed two meta analyses which
included up to 40 studies and these
analyses concluded pretty convincingly
that beta alanine doeses improve
physical performance but the effect is
pretty small and the effect really only
applies with certain physical activities
any exercise or movement that it is
intense and lasts for more than 30
seconds but is too intense to last above
10 minutes so something like Sprints
that can be done for a few minutes but
exhaust the muscles would be a good
example the evidence around beta alling
is robust and often pretty well done but
because of the small effect I couldn't
give it an A so I demoted it to a b it
is good but it's not the best or even
necessary in many
situations creatine for performance
speaking of performance supplements
let's discuss creatine I actually looked
at creatine for older individuals and
the effect supplementation has on bone
and muscle mass as well as strength
don't let the thumbnail fool you it's
true that one of the analyses indicated
no effect of creatine for bone health
but I explained why that might be the
case I'll leave the details for that
video if you're interested on the other
hand another analysis indicated creatine
was beneficial for muscle mass and
strength even in older individuals so if
we pair that with the mountain of
evidence in favor of creatine for
younger individuals too there's
excellent science indicating it provides
a moderate benefit to physical
performance at least resistance training
and high-intensity performance because
of the wealth of evidence and the
moderate effect across multiple metrics
I'd give creatine the gold medal an a
Rola Rosa for cognitive function I
analyzed every human study on rodol Laos
isah for the brain the literature is
scarce at this point of this recording
still I tried it myself and although
utterly unscientific I had a wonderful
experience using it that said several
studies on rodal Rosa are horrible
quality I mean poor methodology uh and
improper statistical analyses used which
weakens the confidence in the scientific
evidence behind rodo Rosa for cognition
there are ever a few wellone studies
that still indicate benefit and
considering the effect size and the wide
reaching benefits it is enticing to give
it one of the higher scores yet in total
while I had a great experience there is
still limited formal evidence in humans
to back it so I'm knocking down two
grades to a c and honestly I'm even
tempted to knock it down three although
I do think that as more better quality
evidence comes available that rating
will
change ninas for cardiovascular health
I'm going to subtype this one because I
reviewed eight studies on ninas in
respect to cardiovascular disease and in
one respect I find that the evidence is
extremely weak and in another I find it
all right so the two subtypes are
reversing plaque buildup in arteries and
the other is on measures like blood
pressure the first plaque in the
arteries there are two studies looking
at atherosclerosis that's a plaque in
arteries reversal one study shows a
pretty strong positive effect and the
other finds no effect the one that found
no effect was methodologically more
rigorous than the one that found an
effect but they may have used too low of
a dose which may explain the lack of
effect overall the evidence surrounding
plaque reversal leaves a
tremendous amount to be desired on the
other hand multiple studies indicate
ninas mildly improves blood pressure and
might improve a few other areas of
cardiovascular health albeit by a very
small amount on the plaque reversing
front if I'm assessing the amount as
well as the quality of the science I'd
give it an F I'm not saying it couldn't
have an effect but but we have no strong
unbiased proof in fact we have a little
bit of poor proof on the other hand I'd
give ninas on blood pressure a c and the
other cardiovascular outcomes a d there
are admittedly a few studies that
indicate Effectiveness but if you look
at the effect sizes it's small and aside
from blood pressure there's a lot of
uncertainty about the other measures
funny story that I'm reminded of just
now I remember covered the topic at the
request of a physionic Insider and they
ultimately got angry with me for my less
than enthusiastic appraisal of the
supplement that they were taking so they
told me that I had a lot to learn and
essentially said that I didn't know what
I was talking about in well let's say uh
less polite ways uh they then promptly
left the community immediately after
that and before we can discuss I found
it funny because I had spent a month
collecting all the studies that I could
find pouring over the data collecting
the funding information for each study
and making sure to be extra careful with
my appraisal and my reward if you will
uh was a loss in income and insults from
the person not in the field telling me
that I didn't know what I was doing in
my own field and that I should get more
educated so I suppose I'll need to get
another PhD there is a tragic comedy
there although I doubt Shakespeare would
have written a play about it anyway on
to the next one Lutine and zanthin for
ey Health this was an area that I knew
very little about so I went out to
educate myself through the analysis of
Six studies and scientific reviews these
two molecules are really interesting I'd
encourage that you check out the
dedicated video on them I go over what
they are and their mechanisms as well as
of course the data anyway there is great
consistency see across studies that I
analyzed not only that the effects are
pretty impressive with uh not only
long-term eye protection but some
improvements in eye function I'll just
State plainly this is another a in my
books and to clarify all the studies use
lutein and zanthin together because they
work slightly differently but work
synergistically check out my video for
the details like I said it's linked in
the pin comment bourin for metabolic
disorder this was also a bit of a roller
coaster because one analysis I went over
uh was so bad that I chucked it in the
trash and even contacted the journal
that was published in because well it
contains so many errors then we went
over another analysis on the topic a
better one although also not perfect and
it seemed that berberin is a benefit in
reducing different clinical markers like
hba1c blood sugar improving insulin
sensitivity and reducing blood fats
there were some uh funny moments in that
investigation again I'll point you to
the dedicated video at any rate I ended
up limiting my conclusions to what these
studies focused on people with type 2
diabetes it might also apply to people
without diabetes but that's unconfirmed
overall bourin seem to have a lot of
studies behind it but not all the
studies are a gold standard randomized
control trial
because there's uh no Placebo control so
I'm tending towards a c on this one but
I wouldn't be mad if we were to upgrade
it to a b that rating may rise as more
better quality studies emerge okay let's
do uh one more thing out of the top
grades a through C let's say how would I
prioritize these if you had a limited
capacity to buy these supplements if
you're looking for just one supplement
creatine has my vote for president if
you want more the three a tier so
creatine ltin and zaz anthon are a
strong Choice then from there likely
omega-3 a lower dose around one gam or
less and then from there nothing I'd
skip the rest not because they don't
work but because if you have a limited
budget or just don't want to be taking
pills and powders these will provide the
biggest bangang for your buck if you did
want to invest more in addition to the
four already mentioned I I'd aim for
toring again keep in mind I'm limiting
the mentions based on the outcomes
assessed we'll see if these get promoted
in score next year as I continue my
investigations into other outcomes but
guess what I have looked at other
supplements in the past and I'll link
another list for you right here
[Music]